hey everyone welcome back to the store
automation playlist and today we are
going to discuss about another
interesting feature which is available
in tracentistoska
so until now we have been automating a
lot of test cases in different
applications but these are mostly
functional test cases right which may be
present in the form of manual test cases
or some requirement document but what
about the test cases which are never
written okay
so Tosca allows you to also do some
exploratory testing now if you have not
heard about exploratory testing it is an
approach to software testing where you
do simultaneous learning test design and
also execution
so there are no predefined test cases
okay through which a tester can check
the system but they go and check the
system on the Fly okay
so the focus of exploratory testing is
to find bugs which will be missed in the
regular manual testing right so this is
a kind of ad hoc testing but it is not
random testing so there are a lot of
ways you can do exploratory testing and
Tosca also provides you with a whole
feature through which you can perform
this explorative testing
so let's see how we can do exploratory
testing using Tosca
so to start with exploratory testing you
need to go into the execution folder and
when you expand this you will find a
folder which is called exploratory
testing okay so here uh we have got
different options we can create a
explorative session we can create a
folder okay or we can import results
file and import results from a session
ID okay but for now we will be going
ahead and creating a explorative session
okay so once you create this exploit
this session there are lots of different
things which are present here okay like
there are exploratory testers we can add
number of testers who will be doing
exploratory testing okay then uh there
are issue proposals so we can link the
scenario we can have a description we
have the session schedule okay so it can
be time boxed from some certain time to
some certain time
okay that could be a admin who will be
the session owner then the session could
be passed failed okay so the session
status you can see it is in planned
right now
then the number of scenarios the
duration the objects and also the email
right
so all of these different details can be
filled uh in expertise session
but the most important part is to uh
create a session document right an
exploratory session document and to do
that we need to open the explorative
scenario manager okay and here you can
record the interactions between your
application and the user
so on the top you will see there is
explorative scenario click on that
okay and then it will ask you what kind
of application you want to record your
interactions and we will be working with
the web application so we will choose
Chrome for now okay and then I'll click
on start and you will see that it will
start recording the interactions okay
now I can go ahead and perform some
interactions with my application and
that will be recorded okay
so I'll click on automobile here and I
will fill some data here okay so in the
background this will also get filled
in the recording okay so let me fill
this out
foreign
so this is what I want to record for now
so I will go here and I will click on
stop to stop the session
and now that will create a particular
scenario document okay so you can see
here this is a a media document where
you have got images along with the
interactions okay so you can see all the
steps which are performed are present on
the left hand side in the form of
scenario steps and then on the right
hand side
of the whole screen has been recorded
okay also the interaction of the user is
recorded so you can see there is an
annotation called click on automobile
okay so this step it says what you need
to do it says click on the try sentence
vehicle insurance and it also shows your
image okay
similarly uh for a drop down it will
tell you to click the drop down and then
select that particular value right so
you can see this is a very detailed
document and if you give it to a person
who doesn't know what he needs to do he
can basically run through this document
and perform the steps and then he can
Mark whether this test case has passed
or failed right so this document can be
useful in many ways it could be used for
exploratory testing also it could be
used as a document for a person who is
very new to the team and he doesn't know
more about the application so you can
provide him this document and then he
can start following the steps to know
more about the application at the same
time he can also perform the steps and
test out the application okay
now this is uh in Tosca you can see this
is the session you can save and close it
okay so it will save it and you can go
into the next session but you can also
export this okay
so you can see here it can be exported
in a docx and a PDF format obviously the
PDF format is more preferred
and then there are items like step and
step values are included you can also
include extra columns okay so what is
the actual result uh what is the action
mode action property right uh the media
is already included uh and also the page
setup
okay so I can export this into a PDF
once you click on that it will ask you
where you want to export it okay so
let's choose a folder here called
training okay and click on OK
now it will start exporting this whole
session into a document and you can see
a PDF document has been created
and this is the scenario documentation
you can see a lot of things have been
also added in this documentation apart
from what was recorded okay so that is a
summary with name uh overall result
number of field steps okay number of
steps and then uh there is the scenario
description with all the different steps
mentioned here right also it has got a
media link you can see here these are
the screenshots okay
and you can see once you go through this
screenshot it will just look like a
video with all the different steps
um one by one right how you have
interacted the application in the same
way
at the end it will also include the
system information okay
so with the operating system and then
the screen resolution
and all the other details of the system
this could be useful sometimes uh when
you are testing or you when you are
trying to reproduce a particular issue
right
and also the recorded applications with
its version right so you can see this
kind of document is pretty useful if you
are doing some expiratory testing or
even if you are reporting any issue and
you can record this interactions give it
to a developer or a business analyst you
can have some questions uh from the
business analyst right so a lot of
things can be done with this document
and it's a really good way of creating
some documentation around your testing
right so placentus Tosca automatically
does it and this could be useful in many
different ways as we discussed
so that's an overview of uh how
exploratory testing can be done in Tosca
there are lots of other options uh which
we'll discuss later but this is the
basic idea of how you can record or
interactions between your application
and the user and then create a document
and this document can be exported into a
PDF
so that's all for this video I hope you
enjoyed it and you learned something new
today keep watching our videos and do
subscribe to our channel so that you
don't miss out on any new videos which
we post on a regular basis
so until the next video keep watching
and keep learning Tosca